Padraic Colum Papers
Padraic Colum Papers
1891-1983
Colum, Padraic, 1881-1972.
5 linear ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, legal and financial material of the Irish-American writer.
4159361
Biographical History
Padraic Colum (1881-1972) was an Irish poet, novelist, playwright, author and collector of folklore.
Born in County Longford in Ireland, Colum was the oldest of eight children. He began to write in his early twenties, quickly establishing a reputation in Irish literary circles. In 1912 he married Mary Gunning Maguire (1884-1957), a fellow student at University College Dublin. Mary, raised by her grandmother Catherine Gunning and educated at St. Louis' Convent in Monaghan, was a noted author and critic in her own right. The couple was friends with many notable figures in Irish national and cultural circles, including poet W. B. Yeats, folkorist Lady Gregory, novelist James Joyce, and political activist Patrick Pearse, who with his brother Willie was executed for his leading role in the 1916 Easter Rising. Prior to her marriage Mary taught at Patrick Pearse's St. Ita's School.
Beginning in 1914 Padraic and Mary spent a great deal of time in the United States, particularly in Woods Hole, Massachusetts and in New York City, where both taught at Columbia University. Mary herself was also an author and critic (see for example "Declaration of Independence: Mary Colum as Autobiographer" by Sandy Sternlicht, in The Courier, Volume XXXII, 1997). Padraic became a U.S. citizen in 1945. Mary died in 1957. Mary's nephew Emmet Greene, son of her sister Bridget, was for many years a close friend of the couple; he eventually took over management of Padraic's schedule and finances, particularly after Padraic suffered a stroke in his late eighties, and served as executor of Padraic's literary estate until his own death in 1983.
Colum's wide-ranging literary output included poems and poem cycles ( The Poet's Circuits), plays ( Thomas Muskerry), song lyrics ("She Moved Through the Fair"), essays, novels ( The Flying Swans), biographies ( Our Friend James Joyce, written with his wife Mary), children's stories and much more.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Padraic Colum Papers consists of material relating directly to Padraic and his wife Mary, writings, and material relating to Padraic Colum's estate after his death in 1972.
Padraic and Mary Colum material consists of correspondence, financial and legal material, and memorabilia. Most of the correspondence is incoming, and encompasses friends, family, and literary colleagues. Family includes Susie Colum Ruth, Padraic's sister; Bridget Greene, Mary's sister (known to her family and friends as Bid, Bidelia, and Delia), including letters to her from their father Charles Maguire; Emmet Greene, Bridget's son and Mary's nephew; and assorted members of the Colum, Maguire, Greene and Gunning families. Notable literary correspondents include editor Louise Seaman Bechtel and authors William Rose Benet, Cyril Clemens, Archibald Macleish and Thornton Wilder. Important political figures include French peace activist Maria Jolas, outspoken anti-Nazi Hubertus Prinz zu Löwenstein, and Irish nationalist Patrick Pearse. The James Joyce folders include a letter from C. G. Jung to Joyce, in which Jung comments on Joyce's Ulysses. Filed under Mary Colum's name are letters to her alone from Van Wyck Brooks, W. Somerset Maugham, and Maxwell Perkins among others; there are also a few fragments of her writings. A small amount of legal and financial material includes taxes, leases, passports and citizenship documents, and a copy of Padraic's will. Memorabilia includes both personal items, such as photographs and address books, as well as items related to Irish history, such as a black ribbon commemorating Irish Parliamentary Party founder Charles Stewart Parnell and a memorial card for Michael O'Callaghan, first Republican mayor of Limerick.
Writings consists primarily of items by Padraic, although there are a small number of items by others. Included here are articles, book reviews, essays, lyrics, novels and stories, plays, poetry, and assorted other pieces.
The bulk of the Padraic Colum Estate material is correspondence between Emmet Greene, Colum's literary executor, and authors or publishers wishing permission to reprint or rebroadcast items of Colum's work. In some cases, such as Macmillan who was one of Colum's primary publishers, files may include contracts and royalty statements. There is also some correspondence related to Padraic's funeral and burial. Financial material includes photocopies of bank statements and lists of bank accounts and a few compiled royalty lists. Legal material contains correspondenec with attorneys on various topics; the Cahill, Stone and Driscoll folder includes a personal letter from Gerald Cahill to Emmet and clippings about Cahill's conviction for embezzlement.
Arrangement of the Collection
Writings is subdivided by type (e.g., articles, book reviews); within each type, items are filed alphabetically by title. Within the other two series, material is filed alphabetically by correspondent or topic.
Separated Material
Several published examples of Colum's work have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941.; Belitt, Ben, 1911-2003.; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963.; Clemens, Cyril, 1902-1999.; Colum, Mary.; Colum, Padraic, 1881-1972.; Delamain, Jacques.; Denson, Alan.; Deutsch, Babette, 1895-1982.; Hillyer, Robert, 1895-1961.; Jolas, M.; Joyce, James, 1882-1941.; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961.; Kennelly, Brendan.; Löwenstein, Hubertus, Prinz zu, 1906-1984.; MacDowell, Marian, 1857-1956.; Maritain, Raïssa.; Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965.; McAleer, Edward C.; Nicholl, Louise Townsend.; Oshima, Shotaro, 1899-; Pearse, Padraic, 1879-1916.; Pearse, William, 1881-1916.; Perkins, Maxwell E. (Maxwell Evarts), 1884-1947.; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963.; Raja Rao.; Robinson, Lennox, 1886-1958.; Russell, George William, 1867-1935.; Saul, George Brandon, 1901-1986.; Toksvig, Signe, 1891-1983.; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975.; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987.; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975.; Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938.; Yeats, Jack B. (Jack Butler), 1871-1957.; Dolmen Press.; Lantern Theatre.; Macmillan & Co.; McGraw-Hill Book Company.; Authors, Irish -- 20th century.; Children's literature, Irish.; Folklore -- Ireland.; Irish literature -- 20th century.; Poets, Irish.; Ireland -- History.; Ireland -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Bank statements.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Manuscripts for publication.; Memorial cards.; Photographs.; Negatives (photographs); Research notes.; Royalty statements.; Slides (photographs); Wills.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eric Sherman, 2014.
Inventory
- Padraic and Mary Colum
  - Correspondence
    - Abbey Theatre, 1962; 1964; letters from Ernest Blythe; program (Box 1)
    - Allen, Annette (Mrs. Hervey Allen), 1950; outgoing, regarding her husband Hervey's death (Box 1)
    - American Irish Association, 1946-1947; 1950; newsletter, drafts of position statements (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Sherwood, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Australia trip, 1967; summary of trip by Padraic; reservation information; letter from Irish Ambassador in Canberra; more (Box 1)
    - A, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Bechtel, Louise, 1957; 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Belitt, Ben, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Benet, William Rose, 1928?; about the death of his wife, Elinor Wylie (Box 1)
    - B, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1962; 1969,; undated (Box 1)
    - Colum, Mary (wife, also known as Mollie)
      - to Padraic, undated; many written on letterhead from St. Ita's School (Box 1)
      - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1923-1925; 1948,; 1954,; undated; includes one letter from wife, ESB (Box 1)
      - Columbia University, 1937; 1941,; 1944-1945,; 1947,; 1951,; 1953 (Box 1)
      - De la Mare, Walter, undated; written by his daughter Florence Thompson at his request expressing his sentiments (Box 1)
      - Hillyer, Robert S., 1947 (Box 1)
      - Howard, William Guild, 1942 (Box 1)
      - Maugham, W. Somerset, undated (Box 1)
      - Neff, Emery, undated (Box 1)
      - Perkins, Maxwell, undated; p. 3 only (Box 1)
      - Washburn, Richard K., 1947 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous incoming, A-Z, majority are letters from readers of her autobiography, Life and the Dream (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous incoming, unidentified (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous outgoing, includes fragments of some of her book reviews, addressed to editors (Box 1)
      - Funeral, memorial, 1957; 1960-1961; Michael Biggs; Niall Montgomery; sympathy cards (Box 1)
      - Writings, 1921-1922; 1938,; undated; letters to the editor, book reviews, partial essay (Box 1)
    - Colum, Mary, 1961; undated (Box 1)
    - Colum, Susie, See Ruth, Susie Colum.
    - Colum family, miscellaneous, brother Dick and wife Rose; brother[?] Donal; sister Eileen; cousin Mary (Box 1)
    - Cowell, Sidney (Mrs. Henry Cowell), 1966 (Box 1)
    - C, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Davies, Betty, 1967-1972; most to Padraic, later to Emmet (Box 1)
    - Delamain, Jacques, 1933 (Box 1)
    - Deutsch, Babette, 1957 (Box 1)
    - The Dial, 1923; undated; Gilbert Seldes; Schofield Thayer (Box 1)
    - Digges, Dudley, 1928; 1946; actor; letters are to "Dear Alice" and "Dear Theodore" (Box 1)
    - Dolmen Press, 1957; 1965,; 1970,; 1972,; 1975; Liam Miller; includes prospectuses for some projects of the press and typescript entitled "Liam Miller Scandal by Emmet" (Box 1)
    - D, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - E, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - F, miscellaneous, includes envelope from Robert Frost but no letter (Box 1)
    - Greene, Bridget Maguire (Bid, Bidelia, Delia), 1923; 1931-1937,; 1942,; 1949,; 1951,; undated; Mary Colum's sister and Emmet Greene's mother; includes letters from Bridget and Mary's father, Charles Maguire, as well as from Padraic and Mary; earliest letter (1923) is from an unidentified "Annie" in Kilmainham Prison to "Dear Mrs Green" (Box 1)
    - Greene, Emmet
      - to/from Padraic, 1935; 1955,; 1958-1971,; undated (Box 1)
      - Family, miscellaneous (Greene, Maguire, Gunning), 1951-1980 (gaps); Bridie (cousin); Catherine Greene (aunt?); Clare Maguire (aunt); Eileen Colum (aunt); Geraldine Gunning; Sr. Maureen Maguire; Nora (cousin); Theresa Green (aunt) (Box 1)
        See also Ruth, Susie Colum.
      - Medical, miscellaneous, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
      - Incoming, miscellaneous, 1951; 1966-1976,; 1981; Monsignor Michael Kelliher, others (Box 1)
      - Outgoing, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - G, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Hayes, Michael, 1952; Irish policeman; much of the letter is about Sinn Féin founder Arthur Griffith (Art Ó Gríobhtha) (Box 1)
    - H, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Irish Tourist Board (Bord Fáilte Eireann), 1965; includes proof of invitation to opening of Thoor Ballylee, home of W. B. Yeats (Box 2)
    - I, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Jolas, Maria, 1941; 1951,; 1965 (Box 2)
    - Joyce, James, 1941; 1947,; undated; letter from Carl Jung to Joyce regarding Ulysses; typescript carbon of letter from an E. Cotton to a Mr. Kastor regarding Mrs. Joyce, with note to Molly (Mary) from "Bob" added in pen at the bottom; photocopy of letter from Joyce to "Dear Ogden" with transcription in pen on reverse; photocopy of Joyce's Swiss death certificate (Box 2)
    - Joyce-related, 1958; 1963,; 1972,; undated; Joyce seminar at Hunter College; clippings; transcripts of Joyce's obituary from microfilm (Box 2)
    - J, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Kennedy, Mary (poet), 1960; 1963 (Box 2)
    - Kirby, Robert, 1971; letters asking Colum for assistance finding a job (Box 2)
      These letters were unopened when the collection was received, and were opened by staff during processing.
    - K, miscellaneous, includes prospectus from Kennikat Press for their "Series on Irish History and Culture" (Box 2)
    - Leeson, Cathy/Kathleen, 1957-1961 (Box 2)
    - de Lima, Agnes, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Löwenstein, Hubertus, Prinz zu, 1944 (Box 2)
    - L, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - MacDonagh, Thomas, 1910 (Box 2)
    - MacDowell, Marian, 1948-1949; 1951,; 1954,; 1972; letters from Marian as well as some material about her and about the MacDowell Colony (Box 2)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1935; 1941,; 1957[?],; 1969 (Box 2)
    - Macmillan, 1931; 1965-1966,; 1970 (Box 2)
      See also Padraic Colum Estate: Correspondence: Macmillan.
    - Maguire, Mary Gunning, See Colum, Mary (wife).
    - Maritain, Raïssa, 1955; in French (Box 2)
    - McGraw-Hill, 1967; 1969 (Box 2)
      See also Padraic Colum Estate: Correspondence: McGraw-Hill.
    - Miller, Liam, See Dolmen Press.
    - Murphy, Ann, 1969-1970; 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - M, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - National Theatre Society, 1967; contract for Thomas Muskerry (Box 2)
    - Nicholl, Louise Townsend, 1957; 1970 (Box 2)
    - Noble and Noble, 1968 (Box 2)
    - N, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - O'Sullivan, Maisie (Maire), 1970 (Box 2)
      See also Padraic Colum Estate: Correspondence: O'Sullivan, Maisie (Maire).
    - Oshima, Shotaro, 1965 (Box 2)
    - O, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Pearse, Patrick (Pádraig Anraí Mac Piarais), 1910-1911; includes petition regarding the establishment of St. Ita's school for girls, as a companion to St. Enda's school for boys (Box 2)
    - Pearse, Willie (Liam Mac Piarais), 1908; in French to unknown recipient (Box 2)
    - Perkins, Maxwell, 1931; from Padraig, about Mary's writing and Perkins' treatment of her (Box 2)
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1957 (Box 2)
    - P, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Rao, Raja, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Robinson, Henry Morton, 1955
    - Robinson, Lennox, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Russell, George W. ("Æ"), 1920; 1932 (Box 2)
    - Ruth, Susie Colum, Padraic's sister
      - to/from Emmet, 1970-1975; undated (Box 2)
      - to/from Padraic, circa 1960-1970, most undated; includes a poem, "Limestone Landscape," by an unknown author (Box 2)
      - to/from others, 1924; 1973; one, very affectionate, from "Sherman" (Box 2)
    - R, miscellaneous, includes postcard in Gaelic with "Raheen Rural Industries" letterhead (Box 2)
    - Salkeld, Blánaid, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Sandkühler, Konrad, 1956; 1959,; 1970 (Box 2)
    - Saul, George Brandon, 1953 (Box 2)
    - S, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Taft, William Howard III, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Toksvig, Signe, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Trausil, Hans, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Wilder, Thornton, 1944; 1948,; undated; letter; reprint of Wilder's essay on Joyce; typescript of essay, "Giordano Bruno's last meal in Finnegan's Wake" (Box 2)
    - Wilson, Edmund, 1947; 1952,; 1957,; 1973 (Box 2)
    - Wolfe, Thomas, 1938; to Maxwell Perkins (Box 2)
    - W, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Yeats, Jack B., 1939; 1941-1942,; 1947-1948; includes copies of transcripts of letters from Colum to W. B. Yeats in 1905-1906; program from W. B. Yeat's memorial service (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, A-Z by first name (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, includes letter on Cuala Industries Ltd. letterhead (Yeats family) as well as a lengthy but incomplete letter discussing Irish "scholar-patriots" and Irish literature (Box 2)
  - Financial
    - Taxes, 1966-1967; 1969; W-2 forms, correspondence (Box 2)
  - Legal
    - Lease for 415 Central Park West, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Passports, citizenship papers (Box 3)
    - Power of attorney for Emmet Greene, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Will, Padraic Colum, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Memorabilia
    - Address books (Box 3)
    - Awards and honors, 1952; 1958 (Box 3)
    - Banner with design from Book of Kells, undated (Oversize 1)
    - "A Bridge of Poetry with Padraic Colum", script for short 20-minute film about and featuring Colum; accompanied by letter from Emmet Greene (Box 3)
    - Clippings
      - About Mary, 1957-1958; undated (Box 3)
      - About Padraic, 1936; 1947,; 1957-1972,; undated (Box 3)
      - Obituaries, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Reviews of Padraic's work, 1937; 1953-1967; alphabetical by work title (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - G. S. Parnell, Irish National League, 1891; black ribbon printed with Parnell's last words, accompanied by note on letterhead of Irish National League (Box 3)
    - Lantern Theatre programs, 1964-1966; productions of Colum's work (Box 3)
    - Michael O'Callaghan, 1921; commemorative/memorial card for first Republican mayor of Limerick (Box 3)
    - Mr. Colum's Greeks, by Lionel Trilling, 1956; reprint (Box 3)
    - Padraic Colum, 1881-1972, by Alan Denson, inscribed by the author to Emmet Greene (Box 3)
    - Padraic Colum, 1881-1972, by Glenway Wescott, 1973; photocopy from Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Letters (Box 3)
    - Photographs
      - of Mary, portrait photograph in academic garb, damaged; several slides in small box (Oversize 1)
      - of Padraic (Box 3)
      - Unidentified (Box 3)
    - Roger D. Casement letter, 1916; photocopy; Casement was the purported author of The Black Diaries circulated after his arrest in 1916 and published in 1959 by Grove Press (Box 3)
    - "To Padraic Colum", undated; poem by unidentified author (Box 3)
    - "Where Honor is Due: A New York Letter" by Vivian Mercier, 1954; account of the presentation to Padraic of the medal of the Irish Academy of Arts and Letters; typescript (Box 3)
    - [untitled, by Edmund Krochalis], undated; recollections of Padraic's visits and their friendship
    - Miscellaneous, about Padraic (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, about others, memorial cards, clippings, catalogs, etc. (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Miscellaneous, clippings and photocopies of clippings; recollections of childhood,etc. (Box 4)
  - Book reviews
    - Book of Living Verse, by Louis Untermeyer, circa 1932; typescript (Box 4)
    - Gerard Manley Hopkins: A Life, by Eleanor Ruggles, circa 1944; typescript (Box 4)
    - I Knock at the Door, by Sean O'Casey, circa 1939; typescript (Box 4)
    - J. B. Yeats: Letters to His Son, by Joseph Hone (ed.), circa 1945; typescript (Box 4)
    - Journals of Kierkegaard, by Alexander Dru (ed.), circa 1958; typescript (Box 4)
    - Kierkegaard Anthology, by Robert Bretall (ed.), circa 1947; typescript (Box 4)
    - Kiltartan History Book, by Lady Gregory (transl., ed.), circa 1910; typescript; page 1 missing (Box 4)
    - My Last Seventy Years, by Henry Goddard Leach, circa 1956; typescript (Box 4)
    - Scholars and Gypsies, by Walter Starkie, circa 1963; typescript (Box 4)
    - Seventy Years a Showman, by George Sanger, circa 1926; typescript (Box 4)
    - The People, Yes, by Carl Sandburg, circa 1936; typescript (Box 4)
    - Three Great Irishman, by Arland Ussher, circa 1953; typescript (Box 4)
    - Twenty Years A'Growing, by Maurice O'Sullivan, 1933; partial photocopy of clipping (Box 4)
    - [unidentified collection], by Liam O'Flaherty, typescript (Box 4)
  - Essays
    - Arthur Lynch: A portrait, typescript (Box 4)
    - The Battle of Dublin, 1014, 1965; reprint from Scandinavian Studies (Box 4)
    - Edwin Arlington Robinson's poetry, typescript, incomplete (Box 4)
    - Fred Higgins, typescript, incomplete (Box 4)
    - George Moore, Esquire, typescript (Box 4)
    - George Santayana, typescript, several drafts, some incomplete (Box 4)
    - It is not wisdom to be only wise, 1933; galleys from The Dublin Magazine (Box 4)
    - John Butler Yeats, typescripts for two different articles (Box 4)
    - John O'Leary, typescript (Box 4)
    - Jonathan Swift, typescript; although the second page has "SWIFT" handwritten at the top, only the first page appears to actually be about Swift (Box 4)
    - Joyce first and last, typescript; original title "Early Joyce" crossed out (Box 4)
    - Kierkegaard, typescripts for several different pieces, one possibly a lecture; some are incomplete (Box 4)
    - The leadership of W. B. Yeats, 1968; longhand draft, may be incomplete (Box 4)
    - My short and simple recollections of George Bernard Shaw, typescript, incomplete (Box 4)
    - Portrait of James Joyce, 1932; typescript (Box 4)
    - St. Augustine and the literature of remembrance, typescript, incomplete (Box 4)
    - Schopenhauer and the cult of the will, typescripts (Box 4)
    - Seamus O'Kelly, typescript, multiple drafts of some pages (Box 4)
    - Sheridan [Richard B. Sheridan], typescripts; multiple drafts of more than one essay (Box 4)
    - Spinoza, typescripts, one incomplete (Box 4)
    - The state vs. the nation, typescript and clipping, same title but different content; clipping is annotated "Excellent JBC" (Box 4)
    - Stephen Phillips, typescript and carbon copy (Box 4)
    - Street song, typescript (Box 4)
    - Theodore Spicer-Simson, blue carbon of typescript (Box 4)
    - Tom Kettle, a memoir, typescript, galleys from The Dublin Magazine, incomplete clipping of published version (Box 4)
    - Whitley Stokes and another, typescripts and blue carbon of different version (Box 4)
    - William James, typescript (Box 4)
  - Letters to the editor
    - Miscellaneous, 1948; 1957,; 1958 (Box 5)
  - Lyrics
    - Miscellaneous, mixture of published sheet music, handwritten drafts, etc.; titles include "Cradle Song" and "Old Woman of the Roads" (Box 5)
  - Notebooks
    Notebooks have no titles; first few words of each are given below.
    - "attaches me...", blue Columbia notebook, approximately 73 handwritten pages which appear to be drafts of a long poem (Box 5)
    - "is attributed to unusually well-informed circles...", brown Paper King spiral notebook, approximately 32 handwritten pages (Box 5)
    - "It is rather a pity...", brown Capital Standard notebook, approximately 48 handwritten pages (Box 5)
    - "Notes for Roman portrait Jan 1968", brown Paper King spiral notebook, approximately 67 handwritten pages on various people and events of Roman history (Box 5)
  - Novels and stories
    - The boy apprenticed to an enchanter: Introduction, typescript carbon (Box 5)
    - The flying swans, scattered fragments, approximately 100 pages total (Box 5)
    - The naming of the land, typescript carbon (Box 5)
    - In Pilver Park there walks a deer, 1969; typescripts, galleys from The New Yorker (Box 5)
    - Julia, typescript, carbon of different version (Box 5)
    - The stone of victory, layout/setting copy for several stories (Box 5)
    - The tradition that existed in my grandmother's house, 1967; typescript carbon (Box 5)
    - Tristan and Iseult, incomplete typescripts of several drafts (Box 5)
    - The voyages, galleys (Box 5)
    - [untitled], typescript carbon; features character named Judy Pat (Box 5)
  - Plays
    - Balloon, typescript carbon in blue binder (Box 5)
    - Cloughoughter, photocopy of typed pages, incomplete (Box 5)
    - Mogu the Wanderer, typescript carbon, incomplete (Box 5)
    - Monasterboice, typescript carbon, one page (Box 5)
    - Thomas Muskerry, typescript, incomplete (Box 5)
    - Ulysses in Night-Town, typescript carbon, one page (Box 5)
  - Poetry
    - A poet's circuits, typescripts, typescript carbons, photocopies of pages with typesetting markup, etc. (Box 5)
    - Images of departure, proofs from Dolmen Press (Box 6)
    - Story of Lowry Maen, typescripts, typescript carbons, handwritten sheets; includes glossary of "people and situations" (Box 6)
    - To Ireland with love (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous poems, single poems, fragments, etc., including drafts of poems from various collections; mix of typescript, typescript carbon, handwritten (Box 6)
  - Travel
    - City of St. Martin, typescript (Box 6)